Akash Kakkilaya

akakkilaya@utexas.edu

2604 Notre Dame Drive • Plano, TX 75093 • (318) 550-6006

Summary

I am a biology major at The University of Texas at Austin, and I am planning on applying to medical school. Over the past few years I have enjoyed working with patients in a variety of settings from clinics, hospitals, and summer camps. I have also tried to further colorectal cancer research Texas A&M and MD Anderson. I want to become a physician, so I can combine these two passions.

Education

The University of Texas at Austin Bachelor of Science and Arts, Biology

May 2020

Overall GPA: 3.91, Dean's List

Relevant Coursework: Biostatistics, Medical Terminology, Computational Biology, Genetics with Lab

Research Experience

The University of Texas at Austin- Lead Research Assistant; Austin, TX

January 2017-Present

- Conducted stimulus-response experiments on *Arabidopsis thaliana* to determine the signaling pathway of extracellular nucleotides and their effect on primary root and root hair growth
- Photographed seedlings with microscope and measured growth with ImageJ software
- Analyzed results with a variety of statistical tools and presented findings with Excel and RStudio
- Trained and supervised students and junior mentors with their experiments, data analysis, and collection
- Developed protocols for various lab procedures and safety measures and implemented them by training others

MD Anderson Cancer Center- NCI R25E Research Assistant; Houston, TX

June 2019-August 2019

- Exploited CRISPRa to modulate the expression of candidate genes that are differentially expressed between benign hyper-proliferations and premalignant polyps
- Transformed *E.coli* with plasmids that contained sgRNA targets sequences of the candidate genes
- Identified positive bacterial colonies with next generation sequencing (NGS)
- Maintained cultures of HEK 293T and HCT 116 cell lines
- Infected HCT 116 cells with a lentiviral vector that contained the CRISPRa constructs and performed RT-qPCR to verify gene expression in candidate genes

Texas A&M University- Research Assistant for summer REU; College Station Texas

May 2017-July 2017

- Identified the molecular mechanisms underlying EGFR-independent colorectal cancer progression
- Assisted with mouse colonoscopies and dissections
- Counted and measured the length of polyps found in the colon and small intestine of mice under a dissection microscope
- Developed skills to handle and breed a mouse colony in compliance with IACUC regulations

Research Output

- Kakkilaya, A. (2020). Discovering the role of eATP and various kinase receptors in the modulation of primary root length in Arabidopsis thaliana (Unpublished undergraduate thesis). The University of Texas at Austin. Austin, TX.
- Bautista, L., Kakkilaya, A., Mir, I., The history of opioid use (abstract). Accepted to Pediatric Academic Societies 2020 Meeting canceled by COVID-19. Philadelphia, PA.
- Kakkilaya, A., Bommi, P., Vilar-Sanchez, E. (2019). CRISPRa mediated expression of candidate genes in Hyperplastic Colorectal Polyps(abstract). Poster at MD Anderson Summer Experience Poster Presentation, Houston, TX
- Kakkilaya, A., Mantilla-Rojas, C., Bourgeois, E., Jaimes, J., Threadgill, D.(2017). The effect of Erbb family on colorectal cancer (abstract). Poster at TAMHSC 2017 Summer Research Program. College Station, TX.

Leadership and Activities

Children's Blood and Cancer Center- Volunteer

September 2019-Current

- Engaged with pediatric oncology patients and their families by playing games, constructing crafts, and conversing
- Completed inventory checks of food, beverages, and medical supplies and restocked items as needed
- Transported blood products to and from the blood bank in compliance with specimen transport protocol
- Coordinated with other volunteers to ensure all toys, furniture, and bedding were cleaned and sanitized

Camp Kesem- Engagement Committee Member

September 2018- Current

- Fundraised over \$1,500 personally and over \$180,000 as an organization to send kids affected by their parent's cancer to summer camp.
- Implemented initiatives to recruit a more diverse group of counselors to the organization.
- Developed programming to make all members feel connected to each other and to the mission of Kesem
- Facilitated support groups between campers so they could help each other throughout the year once Camp ended
- Encouraged children to discuss the issues they faced while their parent had cancer
- Engaged with camp participants through coordinated activities to help distract from challenges they faced at home

Dell Children's Emergency Department- Volunteer

September 2017- December 2019

- Distributed comfort care items such as toys drinks, and snacks to patients and their families
- Assisted triage nurses with registration and organized patient documents in compliance with HIPAA regulations
- Ensured there was adequate patient protective equipment, clean rooms, linens, nutritional items, and wheelchairs, so hospital staff could focus on direct patient care

Peer-Led Undergraduate Studying (PLUS)- Facilitator

September 2018- December 2018

- Led weekly study sessions to clarify concepts for classmates in my introductory biochemistry course
- Collaborated with professor and other facilitators every week to plan and implement learning sessions
- Promoted collaboration among students through weekly quizzes and application problems

Camp Quality- Counselor

July 2018

- Served with other counselors to create an environment where kids who have or have had cancer can find respite and regain their childhood
- Supported kids as they discussed the challenges they faced during treatment and in remission
- Participated in camp activities such as swimming, rock climbing, arts and crafts, and silent disco with the campers

Skills

- R Programming Language/RStudio
- Recruitment of participants for organizations
- Regulatory compliance with BSL2 and IACUC
- Protocol development, implementation, and training
- Lab Techniques: Bacterial cultures, Plasmid isolation, Tissue culture, PCR, CRISPR, PCR, DNA/RNA Extraction, Mouse Handling
- Certifications and Licenses: AED/CPR, CITI, ICH, GCP
- Basic Spanish